Finding Aid for Carolyn S. Burns papers, 1943-1968
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Carolyn S. Burns papers 1943-1968
Burns, Carolyn Sinelli, 1915-
8559 Aa 2
Files relating to her work with Italian-American organizations, especially the American committee on Italian Migration, the American-Italian Business and Professional Women's Club, and the Piemontese Ladies Social Club; papers concerning her interest in U. S. immigration law and the problems of displaced persons and refugees; files relating to her Catholic faith and work for Catholic missionary organizations, notably the Friends of Sts. Peter and Paul Missionaries; and files concerning Democratic Party politics and her work during the 1966 senatorial campaign of G. Mennen Williams.
8 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Carolyn Burns in 1979 (Donor no. 6250 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Detroit civic worker and fund-raiser, active in Italian-American civic and cultural organizations, aid to displaced persons and refugees, immigration law reform and Michigan Democratic Party affairs-notably the 1966 senatorial campaign of G. Mennen Williams.
The papers of Carolyn Sinelli Burns portray a woman with many interests and talents. Particularly gifted as an organizer and fund raiser, Carolyn Burns involved herself with the problems of displaced persons and refugees, with Catholic missionary societies, with immigration law reform, and with Democratic Party affairs. Unifying her many diverse interests is a belief in the dignity of all mankind, a belief she received as part of her Catholic faith.
The Burns' collection is divided into six broad categories: ethnic organizations; immigration reference file; United Nations material; religious material; the 1966 G. Mennen Williams senatorial campaign; and a miscellaneous file.
Subjects:
American Committee on Italian Migration.; American-Italian Business and Professional Women's Club.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.); Piemontese Ladies Social Club (Detroit, Mich.); United States--Congress--Elections--1966.; Michigan--Emigration and immigration.; Italian Americans--Michigan.; Friends of Saints Peter and Paul Missionaries.; Catholic Church--Missions--Societies, etc.; Missionaries.; Clubs--Michigan--Detroit.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; United States--Politics and government--1963-1969.; Refugees--United States.; Catholic Church--Michigan--Detroit.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Italy--Emigration and immigration.; Immigrants--Michigan.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
- Ethnic Organizations 1952-1968
  Most of the ethnic file consists of papers from the American Committee on Italian Migration (ACIM). Founded in 1952, the organization consolidated Italian thinking on immigration law reform and then lobbied within Congress to achieve these reforms. Ms. Burns served as an officer in ACIM's Detroit chapter.
  The Piemontese (sic.) Ladies Social Club (PISC) is also well represented. Founded in Detroit in 1942 (it sprang from the Piemontese Club founded in 1913) the women in this organization sent packages to relatives and friends in the armed forces. At war's end the club was continued as a social organization seeking to preserve family and social ties among those whose families had migrated to America from Italy's Piedmont region. In addition to ACIM and the PLSC, records of the American-Italian Business and Professional Women's Club and Boys' Town of Italy are also filed within this series.
  - American Committee on Italian Migration (Detroit Chapter)
    - 1952
      - ACIM Dispatch (Box 1)
      - Mailing list (Box 1)
      - Meetings (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - National Dinner (New York) (Box 1)
    - 1953
      - ACIM Dispatch (Box 1)
      - Legislation (Box 1)
      - Meetings (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - National Dinner (New York) (Box 1)
    - 1954
      - Chicago Chapter (Box 1)
      - ACIM Dispatch (Box 1)
      - Meetings (Box 1)
      - Midwest Regional Conference (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - National Dinner (New York) (Box 1)
      - National Publicity Kit (Box 1)
    - 1955
      - ACIM Dispatch (Box 1)
      - Detroit Dinner (Box 1)
      - Invitations (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - Program (Box 1)
      - Meetings (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - National Dinner (New York) (Box 1)
      - Utica, Michigan chapter (Box 1)
    - 1956
      - ACIM Dispatch (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - National Dinner (New York) (Box 1)
    - 1957
      - ACIM Dispatch (Box 1)
      - Legislation (Box 1)
      - Mailing list (Box 1)
      - Meetings (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - National Dinner (New York) (Box 1)
      - Summary Report,1952-1957 (Box 1)
    - 1958
      - ACIM Dispatch (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - 1959
      - ACIM Dispatch (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - National Dinner (New York) (Box 1)
      - Washington, D.C. Symposium (Box 1)
    - 1960
      - ACIM Dispatch (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - 1961
      - ACIM Dispatch (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - National Dinner (New York) (Box 2)
      - Rome (Italy) Symposium (Box 2)
    - 1962
      - ACIM Dispatch (Box 2)
      - Legislative matters (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - 1963
      - Correspondence (Box 2)
      - ACIM Dispatch (Box 2)
      - Membership (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - Washington, D.C. Symposium (Box 2)
    - 1964
      - ACIM Dispatch (Box 2)
      - Financial information (Box 2)
      - Meetings (Box 2)
      - Membership (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - 1965
      - Contributions (1957-1965) to National (Box 2)
      - ACIM Dispatch (Box 2)
      - Meetings (Box 2)
      - Membership (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - National Symposium (Box 2)
      - Press releases (Box 2)
    - 1966-1967
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - American-Italian Business and Professional Women's Club (Amit Club)
    - Activities and clippings (Box 2)
    - AMIT Bulletin (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Membership lists (Box 2)
    - Membership recruitment (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Boys Town of Italy (Box 2)
  - Italian Flood Relief
    - 1951, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1952 (Box 2)
  - Italian Medical Relief (Box 2)
  - Italian Red Cross (Box 2)
  - Italian War Veterans (W.W.I) (Box 2)
  - Piemontese Club (Box 2)
  - Piemontese Ladies Social Club
    - Undated constitution and membership lists (Box 2)
    - 1954 (Box 2)
    - 1954 miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - 1954 aid to children mutilated during W.W. II (Box 2)
    - 1955
      - Financial (Box 2)
      - Minutes and reports (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - 1956 (Box 2)
    - 1957 (Box 2)
    - 1958 (Box 2)
    - 1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960 (Box 2)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 2)
    - 1963-1968 (Box 2)
- Immigration Reference File 1950-1967
  The immigration reference file contains items relating to immigration and the amending of U.S. immigration law. The material comes from a number of sources including the Michigan Commission on Displaced Persons (later the Michigan Commission on Displaced Persons and Refugees), the Michigan Committee on Immigration, Detroit's
  International Institute, the American Immigration and Citizenship Conference, and the Mayor's Commission on Displaced Persons and Refugees (Detroit). Within this category, material from the Mayor's Commission and the folders entitled "Communist Organizations" are particularly interesting. The Mayor's Commission helped resettle refugees who had fled from Hungary after the failure of the 1956 revolt. "Communist Organizations" folders detail the considerable lengths taken by non-communist groups, to differentiate themselves from organizations they believed to be communist or communist fronts.
  - 1950
    - Michigan Commission on Displaced Persons (Box 3)
  - 1952
    - Democratic Party (Box 3)
    - "Exul Familia" (Papal Document) (Box 3)
    - Michigan Commission on Displaced Persons (Box 3)
    - Michigan Committee on Immigration (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - National Conference of Catholic Charities, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Statements made before President's Commission on (Box 3)
    - Immigration, Detroit hearings, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1953
    - Communist Organizations (Box 3)
    - Michigan Committee on Immigration (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - 1954
    - American Resettlement Council for Italian Refugees (Box 3)
    - Communist Organizations (Box 3)
    - Michigan Commission on Displaced Persons (Box 3)
    - Michigan Committee on Immigration, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1955
    - Communist Organizations (Box 3)
    - Edward Lorsi (Detroit visit) (Box 3)
    - Democratic Party (Box 3)
    - Michigan Commission on Displaced Persons (Box 3)
    - Michigan Committee on Immigration (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - 1956
    - Asian American Panel Discussion (Box 3)
    - Communist Organizations (Box 3)
    - Democratic Party (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Refugee Relief Program, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1957
    - Common Council for American Unity (Box 3)
    - Democratic Party (Box 3)
    - Mayor's Commission on Displaced Persons and Refugees (Detroit) (Box 3)
    - Michigan Commission on Displaced Persons and Refugees (Box 3)
    - Midwest Immigration Conference (Box 3)
  - 1958
    - American Immigration and Citizenship Conference (Box 3)
  - 1960
    - Michigan Commission on Displaced Persons and Refugees (Box 3)
    - Michigan Committee on Immigration (Box 3)
  - 1961
    - American Immigration and Citizenship Conference (Box 3)
  - 1962
    - American Immigration and Citizenship Conference (Box 3)
    - American Council for Nationalities Service (Box 3)
  - 1963
    - American Immigration and Citizenship Conference (Box 3)
    - Conference on Immigration and Economic Growth (Box 3)
    - Council on Religion and International Affairs (Box 3)
    - Democratic Party (Box 3)
    - Michigan Committee on Immigration (Box 3)
  - 1964
    - American Immigration and Citizenship Conference (Box 3)
  - 1965
    - American Immigration and Citizenship Conference (Box 4)
    - Florence Cassidy (Box 4)
    - Michigan Committee on Immigration, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - National Committee for Immigration Reform (Box 4)
    - Dean Rusk (Detroit visit) (Box 4)
  - 1966
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - 1967
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
- United Nations Material 1955-1968
  The United Nations file deals primarily with the annual celebration of U.N. Week in the Detroit-Windsor area. Some items also pertain to the sponsoring of annual model United Nations.
  - 1955 (Box 4)
  - 1956 (Box 4)
  - 1957 (Box 4)
  - 1958 (Box 4)
  - 1959 (Box 4)
  - 1960
    - U.N. Week (Box 4)
    - U.N. Bridge ceremony.(Detroit) (Box 4)
  - 1961
    - U.N. Week, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Contributions (Box 4)
    - Detroit chapter, AAUN (Box 4)
  - 1962-1968 (Box 4)
- Religious material 1943-1968
  Among the religious material are several interesting and a few unique items. Unique are notes taken over the course of many years by Ms. Burns during personal retreats. Almost every year for nineteen years she took eight days to listen to the presentations of priests and nuns and to reflect upon her own spiritual development. The notes she took during these retreats are often quite detailed and reflect both upon her own faith and the character of Catholicism.
  Of interest in this series are materials from the Friends of Saints Peter and Paul, Missionaries. The Missionaries of Sts. Peter and Paul form the American province of the Catholic Pontifical Institute of Mission Extension. The friends raised funds to support the missionaries efforts to convert third world peoples to Catholicism. Ms. Burns was deeply involved in organizing many of these fundraising events.
  - Council of Catholic Women (national and Detroit)
    - 1956 (Box 4)
    - 1957 (Box 4)
    - 1958 (Box 4)
    - 1959 (Box 4)
    - 1960 (Box 4)
    - 1961 (Box 4)
    - 1962 (Box 4)
    - 1963 (Box 4)
    - 1964, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1965 (Box 4)
    - 1966 (Box 4)
    - 1967 (Box 4)
    - 1968 (Box 4)
  - The Friends of Sts. Peter and Paul Missionaries
    - 1951 (Box 4)
    - 1952 (Box 4)
    - 1953 (Box 4)
    - 1954 (Box 4)
    - 1955
      - Fiesta (Box 4)
      - Italian classes (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - Danny Thomas Dinner (Box 4)
    - 1956
      - George Meany Testimonial (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - 1957 (Box 5)
      - Dinner (Box 5)
      - Fiesta (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - 1958 (Box 5)
    - 1959 (Box 5)
    - 1960 (Box 5)
    - 1961 (Box 5)
    - 1962 (Box 5)
  - Personal Retreats
    - 1943 (Box 5)
    - 1944 (Box 5)
    - 1945 (Box 5)
    - 1947 (Box 5)
    - 1948 (Box 5)
    - 1949 (Box 5)
    - 1950 (Box 5)
    - 1952 (Box 5)
    - 1953 (Box 5)
    - 1954 (Box 5)
    - 1955 (Box 5)
    - 1956 (Box 5)
    - 1957 (Box 5)
    - 1958 (Box 5)
    - 1959 (Box 5)
    - 1960 (Box 5)
    - 1961 (Box 5)
    - 1962 (Box 5)
    - 1965 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Religious material
    - Christ Child Society (Box 5)
    - Gesu Parish, Detroit, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Other Detroit Area Parishes (Box 6)
    - Fr. Kelly Appeals (Box 6)
    - Bishop Fulton J. Sheen (Box 6)
    - Notes and Axioms (Box 6)
    - Women (Box 6)
- Democratic Party material 1933-1966
  In 1966 Carolyn Sinelli Burns was responsible for the scheduling of all persons involved in the G. Mennen Williams senatorial campaign, including Williams himself. Among the documents she retained after the campaign's unsuccessful conclusion was the master file of 11regrets", that is requests for an appearance by Williams which were rejected.
  - 1933 (Box 6)
  - 1934
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Northwestern (Detroit) Italian American Democratic Assoc. (Box 6)
    - Women's Wayne County Lacy for Governor Committee (Box 6)
  - 1935-1939 (Box 6)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 6)
  - 1944 (Box 6)
  - 1945 (Box 6)
  - 1946-1948 (Box 6)
  - 1949 (Box 6)
  - 1950
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Printed Dinner Programs (Box 6)
    - Printed material (Box 6)
  - 1951
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Printed Dinner programs (Box 6)
  - 1952
    - Campaign literature (Box 6)
    - Jefferson study club (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - 1953 (Box 6)
  - 1954
    - Newsclippings (Box 6)
    - State Central Committee Women's Division (Box 6)
  - 1955 (Box 6)
  - 1956 (Box 6)
  - 1957 (Box 6)
  - 1958 (Box 6)
  - 1960
    - Campaign Literature (Box 6)
    - Directory (Box 6)
    - Displaced persons and refugees (Box 6)
    - Fall Convention (state party) (Box 6)
    - Legislative kit (Box 6)
    - Nationalities Division (Box 6)
    - Pastore, John D. (Detroit visit) (Box 6)
    - Platform committee Detroit hearings (Box 6)
    - "Strategy for Peace" program (Box 6)
  - 1961 (Box 6)
  - 1962 (Box 6)
  - 1964
    - Fall convention (state) (Box 7)
    - Hart Campaign
      - Legislative record (Box 7)
      - PAH Scheduling
        - September 26-October 24 (Box 7)
        - October 25-November 3 (Box 7)
        - Schedule distribution (Box 7)
    - Legislative Campaign kit (Box 7)
    - Legislative Campaign kit (supplemental) (Box 7)
    - Women's conference (Box 7)
    - Women's Day (Wayne County, January 25)
      - 1966 (Box 7)
    - Jefferson-Jackson dinner (Box 7)
    - G. Mennen Williams 1966 Campaign
      - Master File GMW "Regrets"
        - Explanatory material (Box 7)
        - A (Box 7)
        - B (Box 7)
        - C (Box 7)
        - D (Box 7)
        - E (Box 7)
        - F (Box 7)
        - G (Box 7)
        - H-I (Box 7)
        - J (Box 7)
        - K (Box 7)
        - L (Box 7)
        - M (Box 7)
        - Mc (Box 7)
        - N (Box 7)
        - O (Box 7)
        - P-Q (Box 7)
        - R (Box 7)
        - S (Box 7)
        - T (Box 7)
        - U (Box 7)
        - V (Box 7)
        - W (Box 7)
        - Y (Box 7)
        - Z (Box 7)
      - Philip Hart
        - Schedule Distribution (Box 7)
        - PAH Schedule
          - October 16-22 (Box 7)
          - October 23-26 (Box 7)
          - October 27-31 (Box 7)
          - November 1-5 (Box 7)
          - November 6-11 (Box 7)
          - Form letters (Box 7)
          - Memos Speeches (Box 7)
      - Gery Williams schedule (Box 7)
      - Zolton A. Ferency schedule (Box 7)
  - Undated re. JFK House Building Fund Drive (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous file
  Finally, a miscellaneous file was created for a number of interesting documents, including a folder of records from the Detroit Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy, printed material from Sheet Metal Workers Local 281, and the material of the Michigan Democratic Party's "J.F.K. House" building fund drive.
  - Detroit Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy (Box 8)
  - Italian participation in Detroit's 250th anniversary celebration (1951) (Box 8)
  - One hundredth Anniversary celebration of Italy's unification (Box 8)
  - Sheet Metal Workers Local no. 281 (Box 8)
  - Unions (Detroit Area) (Box 8)
  - University District Community Association (Box 8)
  - Testimonial Dinners, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Visit of Italian Prime Minister Alcide de DeGasperi to Detroit (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Photographs